Welcome to the evocative hall of Candelabras, so named because the Spilio Thames found in
this section of the route, resemble, in shape and color.
Elegan 19th century Candelabras, with wax seemingly dripping slowly from the candles.
We are now in the first of the four halls we will visit along a route of approximately
one kilometer.
In reality, however, the Grotta del Boe-Marino is part of a much larger car's system.
The cave you are visiting today connects through underground galleries to three other cavities,
the Grotta de Supalu, the Grotta de Sumo-Lente, and the Grotta de Montelongos.
There are therefore four external entrances leading to a single vast underground system,
with approximately 75 kilometers explored so far.
It is important to stress this.
The system is still being explored.
We do not yet know its true extent, with its 75 kilometers already documented, it is currently
the second longest car's system in Italy.
The Grotta del Boe-Marino is the only part of the system accessible to the public and is
divided into three branches.
The Northern Branch, approximately 9 kilometers long, currently closed to the public.
The central branch, 5 kilometers long, accessible only to cave divers.
The Southern Branch, 8 kilometers long.
The one we are visiting today, of which only the first kilometer has been open to visitors
since 1983, the year of its first public opening.
The Southern Branch is still active.
Along the route you will notice dripping water, a sign that the formations are still slowly
developing.
The cave is constantly changing, even if imperceptibly, to our eyes.
But the cave also changes through another far more powerful force, the erosive action
of an underground river that still flows today and continues to carve out these galleries.
For almost the entire length of our route, there is sea water beneath our feet.
At the end of the route, we will instead encounter an underground river.
A head of us will flow fresh, clear and silent water.
It is precisely this water course that is the principle architect of the entire car's
system.
Through its erosive force exerted over millions of years, it has carved through the limestone,
shaping galleries, widening cavities, and contributing to the formation of most of the
75 kilometers explored to date.
As you walk through these halls, try to imagine a time when the spaces you see were completely
submerged.
During the early stages of its formation, the cave was filled with fresh water right up to
the ceiling.
The mighty underground river occupied every space, exerting a continuous erosive action
on the rock in its slow and ceaseless journey in search of a natural outlet.
That outlet was found at the sea.
The current entrance to the Grata del Boe marino coincides in fact with the mouth of that
underground river, the terminal stretch of a vast system shaped by water over geological
time.
When the river opened its outlet to the sea, the water level inside the cave gradually
dropped.
The halls emptied and the sea became part of the underground environment.
Only then dropped by drop in silence and darkness did all the formations you see today
begin to slowly grow and take shape.
What we are observing is not simply a cave, but the result of a long and uninterrupted
dialogue between water and stone.
Natural work of art shaped by the silent force of a river hidden in the heart of the mountain.